Leser, Paul; Papers ger058
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser, 1914-1979; 7; 8 cubic ft. 253 file folders
  - "P.P. (Das schrieb man vor 70 Jahren...)", Undated; Manuscript. (Box 49 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 42)
  - "Paul Honigsheim 1885-1963". Typescripts, proofs, Undated (Box 49 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 43)
  - "Paul Honigsheim 1885-1963", (1968); Reprints. (Box 49 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 44)
  - "Pflüge von Wehr", (1925); reprints, photocopies (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 1)
  - "Der Pflug von Dabergotz", (1925); reprints, photocopies (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 2)
  - "Plow Complex, Culture Change and Cultural Stability", (September 1956); typescripts, proofs (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 3)
  - "Plow Complex, Culture Change and Cultural Stability", (September 1956); Reprints. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 4-5)
  - "Post-Graebner Scholars: Critical, Orthodox, Deviating". Advertisement of lecture, Undated (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 6)
  - "Problems in the Reconstruction and Classification of Ancient Cultures", Undated; Manuscript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 7)
  - "Recht und Ordnung im Jahre 1728", (August 30 1968); clippings, photocopies, typescript (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 8)
  - "Rheinische Pflüge", (February 1927); reprints, photocopies (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 9)
  - "Schwedische Eigenheiten". Lecture notes, Undated (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 10)
  - "Some post-Graebner scholars: critical, orthodox, deviating". Typescript of a lecture, Undated (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 11)
  - "Southern View Reconsidered", (June 17 1963); clippings, typescript (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 12)
  - "Spitteler", (January 7 1925); Clippings. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 13)
  - "Syllabus. How do you know? Exercises in Critique of Sources". Course syllabus, written with Ford Battles, Undated; Typescript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 14)
  - "Das Theater um die blaue Blume", Undated; Typescript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 15)
  - "Thema: Konfirmandenunterricht", (May 1978); clippings, typescript (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 16)
  - "To Attract Teachers", (December 16 1955); Photocopy. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 17)
  - "Tod eines grossen Völkerkundlers", (July 12 1968); clippings, photocopies (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 18)
  - "Verschiedene Erträge von Pflug und Spaten?", Undated; typescripts, photos (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 19)
  - "Verwertungs-A.-G. fuer menschliche Leichen", Undated; Typescript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 20)
  - "Vitae". Typescripts, Undated (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 21)
  - "Völker, Rassen, Sprachen", Undated; Manuscript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 22)
  - "Vom Mittelmeer nach Südostasien", (1931); Reprints. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 23)
  - "Was heist 'Hochkultur'?", Undated; typescript, notes (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 24)
  - "Was ist 'anthropology'?", (May 21 1966); Manuscript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 25)
  - "Was sind 'Arier'?", Undated; Typescript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 26)
  - "Weltgeschichte der Erziehung", Undated; Typescript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 27)
  - "Der Wertbrief am Sonntag", (March 21 1930); clipping (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 28)
  - "Westöstliche Landwirtschaft", (1928); reprints, photocopies (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 29)
  - "Wie Kinder getragen warden", (October 1933); Reprints. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 30)
  - "'Wilde' Erziehung", Undated; Manuscript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 31)
  - "Wutschnaubendes Klagelied (zur Entschuldigung fuer mein langes Schweigen)", (February 1976); typescript, manuscript (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 32)
  - "Zum Geleit", (1957); Reprints. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 33)
  - "Zur Geschichte des Wortes Kulturkreis", (1963); Typescript. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 34)
  - "Zur Geschichte des Wortes Kulturkreis", (1963); Reprints. (Box 50 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 35)
  - "Zur Geschichte des Wortes Kulturkreis", (1963); Reprints. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 1)
  - "Zwanzig Jahre spaeter: Der 'Kinsey Report'", (1968); Typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 2)
  - Chapel talks. Manuscripts and typescripts of lectures, Undated (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 3-4)
  - Balassa, I. Getreidebau in Ost- und Mitteleuropa, (review 1969); reprints, typescripts (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 5)
  - Beiträge zur Volkskunde, (review 1962); Reprints, typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 6)
  - Berg, Gösta. Den Svenska sädesharpan och den Kinesiska, (review 1929?); Reprint. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 7)
  - Bratanic, Branimir. Some similarities between ards of the Balkans, Scandinavian, and Anterior Asia, and their methodological significance, (review 1956); reprints, photocopies, typescript (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 8)
  - Curwen, E. Cecil & Hatt Gudmund. Plough and pasture, (review 1954); typescript, manuscript notes (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 9)
  - Curwen, E. Cecil & Hatt Gudmund. Plough and pasture, (review 1954); Reprints. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 10)
  - Engel, Eduard. Entwechselung, (review 1968); clipping, photocopies (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 11)
  - Filchner, Wilhelm. Hui-Hui. Asiens Islamkämpfe, (review 1928); clipping, photocopies (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 12)
  - Frazer, James George. Mensch, Gott und Unsterblichkeit, (review 1932); Reprints. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 13)
  - Görz, G. Ueber den urgeschichtlichen Pflug von Georgsfeld, (review 1932?); Photocopy. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 14)
  - Heine-Geldern, Robert. Review, Undated; Typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 15)
  - Helwig, Werner. Reise ohne Heimkehr, (review 1954); clipping (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 16)
  - Honko, Lauri. Krankheitsprojektile, (review 1959); reprints, photocopies, typescript (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 17)
  - Hultkrantz, A. The Aims of Anthropology, (review 1968); photocopies, typescripts (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 18)
  - Jensen, A. E. Myth and Cult, (review 1965); photocopies, typescripts (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 19)
  - "Juvenito und sein Nachfolger", (review 1924); Clippings. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 20)
  - Levin, M. G. History, evolutionism and diffustion, (review 1956) (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 21)
  - Lips, Julius. Einleitung in die Vergleichende Völkerkunde, (review 1931); typescript, reprints (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 22)
  - Müller, Werner. Die ältesten amerikanischen Sintfluterzählungen, (review 1930); Typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 23)
  - Murdoch, George. Africa. Its Peoples and Their Culture History, (review 1960); typescript, proofs (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 24)
  - Murdoch, George. Africa. Its Peoples and Their Culture History, (review 1960); Reprints. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 25)
  - Notes and Queries on Anthropology, (review 1952); Reprints, typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 26)
  - Ratzel, Federico. Las Razas Humanes, Undated; Typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 27)
    Review.
  - Rosinger, Lawrence K. et al. The State of Asia, (review 1952); Reprints, photocopies. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 28)
  - Sauer, Marc-R. Les Races de l'Europe, (review 1954); Reprints, typescript. (Box 51 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 29)
  - Schmidt, P. Wilhelm. Handbuch der kulturhistorischen Ethnologie, (review 1937); typescript, manuscript notes (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 1)
  - Schmidt, P. Wilhelm. Handbuch der kulturhistorischen Ethnologie, (review 1937); Reprints. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 2)
  - Schmidt, P. Wilhelm. Der Ursprung der Gottesidee, (review 1959); reprints, typescripts (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 3)
  - Schmidt, P. Wilhelm. Wege der Kulturen, (review 1955); Reprints. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 4)
  - Schmitz, Carl A. Historische Probleme in Nordost-Neuguinea, Huon Halbinsel, (review 1960); reprints, proofs (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 5)
  - Schwidetzky, Ilse. Grundzüge der Völkerbiologie, (review 1950); Reprints, typescript. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 6)
  - Söderbäck. Rågöborna, (review 1940); Photocopies. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 7)
  - Steensberg, Axel (ed.). Dogligliv i Danmark i det nittende og tyvende århundrede, (review 1963); Reprints, typescript. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 8)
  - Teßmann, Günther. Menschen ohne Gott, (review 1928); clippings, photocopies (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 9)
  - Theodoratus, Robert J. Europe: A Selected Bibliography, (review 1969); Typescripts. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 10)
  - Theodoratus, Robert J. Europe: A Selected Bibliography, (review 1969); Reprints. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 11)
  - Völkerkunde: zwölf Vorträge zur Einführung in ihre Probleme, (review 1960); typescript, proofs (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 12)
  - Völkerkunde: zwölf Vorträge zur Einführung in ihre Probleme, (review 1960); Reprints. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 13)
  - Weinert, Hans. Der geistige Aufstieg der Menschheit vom Ursprung bis zur Gegenwart, (review 1952); Reprints, typescript. (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 14)
  - Weiß, Carl. Pädagogische Soziologie, (review 1931); reprints, photocopies (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 15)
  - Wilson, Monica. For men and Elders, (review 1979); reprints, photocopies (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 16)
  - Winthuis, J. Einführung in die Vorstellungswelt primitive Völker, (review 1932); reprint, photocopies, typescript (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 17)
  - Wirz, Paul. Der Totenkult auf Bali, (review 1928); clipping (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 18)
  - Bibliography Paul Leser. On the occasion of his 80th birthday on February 23, 1979. Edited by Absalom Vilakazi. West Hartford, CT: University of Hartford, multiple copies (Box 52 (7-Series 7 - Writings of Paul Leser), Folder 19)
- Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection, 1909-1980; 8; 75 file folders
  The Graebner series is of interest to researchers in the history of anthropology and ethnology, and specifically those concerned with the cultural-historical approach to ethnology which Graebner spearheaded. Graebner was Leser's mentor and perhaps the greatest influence on his academic career and scholarly interests; Leser remained loyal to Graebner's anthropological methodology even after it had fallen out of favor in academic circles.
  Graebner was born in 1877 in Berlin. He received his Ph.D. in history at the University of Berlin in 1901; his dissertation was on a topic in medieval history. He went on to become a research assistant on the staff of the Royal Museum of Ethnology in Berlin, where he classified South Seas materials. In 1907, he became an assistant at the Raustenstrauch-Joest Museum. During this time, he, along with Bernhard Ankermann, developed the method of Kulturkreis, which examined the geographical diffusion of clusters of cultural traits. This development represented a break from the biological-evolutionary concepts which dominated anthropology at the time. Graebner thus remained true to his historical training and became one of the principal exponents of the cultural-historical approach to ethnology. Although this methodological approach was later abandoned by ethnologists, Graebner did exert lasting influence on ethnology in central and northern Europe, particularly on the Vienna school of Kulturkreislebre. In the later years of his life, he became the director of the Raustenstrauch-Joest Museum; he was forced to resign this position due to illness in 1928. In 1934, he returned to Berlin, where he died.
  The series contains important published and unpublished manuscripts, photographs, and some correspondence (1920--1937) of both Graebner and his wife Paula. It also contains materials related to the articles written by Joseph Henninger and Paul Leser in honor of the 100th anniversary of Graebner's birth in 1977. Above all, the series helps illuminate the importance of Fritz Graebner, the man and the ethnologist, in the life and work of his student Paul Leser.The Graebner series is divided into two subseries and arranged alphabetically within the subseries. The series is divided into materials by Graebner and materials about Graebner. Materials by Graebner include: correspondence, photographs/negatives, book reviews, offprints, notebooks, and published and unpublished manuscripts. Materials about Graebner include: correspondence between Leser and Henninger, notes for Leser's writings on Graebner, newspaper articles by Leser about Graebner, and writings by both Leser and Henninger.
  Arranged alphabetically within two series.
  - Writings of Fritz Graebner, original manuscripts, 8.1
    - Nachlass I. Includes manuscripts and notes of "Die Urvölker in ihrer Bedeutung für die Menschheitsgeschichte", Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 1-2)
    - Nachlass II, Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 3-4)
    - Nachlass III, Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 5)
    - Nachlass IV, Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 6)
    - Untitled notebook, Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 7)
    - "Ethnologie". Bound typescript with corrections, Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 8)
    - "Schiller als Geschichtsphilosoph. Vortrag", Undated; original manuscript, photocopies (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 9)
  - Publications by Fritz Graebner, 8.2
    - "Der afrikanische Schild", (1923/1924); Photocopy. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 10)
    - Böhmische Politik vom Tode Ottokars II. bis zum Aussterben der P?emysliden. Dissertation, 1901; multiple copies (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 11)
    - "Causality and Culture", Undated; Photocopy. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 12)
    - "Ein Teil des melanesischen Sprachtypus und seine Träger". Reprint, Undated (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 13)
    - "Eine Zosimosquelle", (1905); Reprint. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 14)
    - "Der Erdofen in der Südsee", (1913); Reprint. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 15)
    - "Ethnographie". Section from book, (1922) (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 16)
    - "Handel bei Naturvölkern", (1910); Photocopy. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 17)
    - "Krückenruder", (1913); Reprint. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 18)
    - "Kunst und Wissen. Der Ursprung des Staates", (1923); Photocopy. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 19)
    - "Marinestabsarzt Dr. Emil Stephan", (1909); Photocopy. (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 20)
    - Metodología Ethnológica, (1940) (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 21)
      Spanish translation, photocopy.
    - El Mundo del hombre primitive, (1925) (Box 53 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 22)
      Spanish translation of Das Weltbild der Primitiven, photocopy.
    - "Noch einmal P. Schmidt und die südostaustralische Kulturgeschichte", (Undated); Photocopy. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 1)
    - "Prof. Haberlandts Kritik der Lehre von den Kulturschichten und Kulturkreisen", (1911); Reprints. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 2)
    - "Thor und Maui", (1919/1920); Reprint. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 3)
    - "Ueber die Theorien von der Herkunft der Arier", (Undated); Photocopy. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 4)
    - "Wanderung und Entwicklung sozialer Systeme in Australien", (1906); Reprints. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 5)
    - "Zur australischen Religionsgeschichte. Eine kritisch-methodische Studie", (December 16 1909); Photocopy. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 6)
    - "Zur Wissenschaftslehre", (1903); Photocopy. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 7)
    - Correspondence of Fritz Graebner, 1920-1930 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 8)
    - Recommendation letter by Graebner for Paul Leser, 1926 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 9)
    - Correspondence of Paul Leser with Graebner family members, 1934-1937 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 10)
    - Correspondence of Paul Leser with Paul & Margarete Graebner, 1977-1980 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 11)
    - Correspondence of Paul Leser with B. G. Teubner Verlag, 1930 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 12)
    - Reviews of Graebner's writings, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 13)
    - Lexicon entries on Fritz Graebner, bibliographic entries, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 14)
    - Sections in books on Graebner, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 15)
    - Clippings on Graebner, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 16)
    - Obituaries on Graebner, 1934 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 17)
    - Photographs of Graebner, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 18)
    - Henninger, P. Joseph. Correspondence with Paul Leser, 1977 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 19)
    - Henninger, P. Joseph. Typescripts of articles on Graebner, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 20)
    - Henninger, P. Joseph. Seminar on P. Wilhelm Schmidt, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 21)
    - Henninger, P. Joseph. "Die kulturhistorische Methode von Fritz Graebner", (1969) (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 22)
    - Leser, Paul. Notebooks from Graebner lectures, 1919-1921 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 23)
    - Leser, Paul. Notebooks from Graebner lectures, 1922 (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 24)
    - Leser, Paul. Notebooks from Graebner lectures, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 25)
    - Leser, Paul. Typescripts of Graebner articles, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 26)
    - Leser, Paul. "Der Bahnbrecher". Typescripts, Undated (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 27)
    - Leser, Paul. "Bemerkungen zu den Bildern", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 28)
    - Leser, Paul. "Einleitung und Schluss", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 29)
    - Leser, Paul. "Der Forscher", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 30)
    - Leser, Paul. "Graebners Arbeitsweise", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 31)
    - Leser, Paul. "Graebners Lebenswerk", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 32)
    - Leser, Paul. "Graebners Verhältnis zu Bernheim", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 33)
    - Leser, Paul. "Graebners Vorläufer und Anreger", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 34)
    - Leser, Paul. "Kulturkreis", Undated; Typescript. (Box 54 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 35)
    - Leser, Paul. "Kulturwandel, Kulturstillstand, Kulturverfall", Undated; Manuscript. (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 1)
    - Leser, Paul. "Der Lehrer", Undated; Typescript. (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 2)
    - Leser, Paul. "Märchen, Missverständnisse, Irrtümer", Undated; Typescript. (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 3)
    - Leser, Paul. "Der Museumsmann", Undated; Typescript. (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 4)
    - Leser, Paul. "Noch einmal Graebner", Undated; Manuscript. (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 5)
    - Leser, Paul. "Der Professor", Undated; Typescript. (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 6)
    - Leser, Paul. "Wiederentdeckung der Graebnerschen Methode". Manuscript, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 7)
    - Leser, Paul. Notes on Graebner from a conference, Chicago, 1947 (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes & materials on Graebner, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 9-11)
    - Graebner, Norman. Clippings, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 12)
    - Graebner, Otto. Materials, notes, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 13)
    - Graebner, Paul. Materials, notes, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 14)
    - Graebner, Robert. Publications, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 15)
    - Graebner, Th. Publications, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 16)
    - Materials on Graebner's contemporaries, Undated (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 17)
    - Graebner, John. Correspondence with Paul Leser, 1980 (Box 55 (8-Series 8 - Fritz Graebner Collection), Folder 18)
- Series 9 - Julius Lips Collection, 1926-1940; 9; 134 file folders